<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: diy | jessica's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://spacekat.github.com/blog/categories/diy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://spacekat.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-23T17:09:33-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://spacekat.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jessica Allen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Steel Pipe Standing Desk]]></title>
    <link href="http://spacekat.github.com/blog/2012/07/31/steel-pipe-standing-desk/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-31T12:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://spacekat.github.com/blog/2012/07/31/steel-pipe-standing-desk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Galvanized steel pipe frame with oak desktop</h2>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/from-above.jpg" title="From above" ></p>

<p>For my coworker Andrew, I wanted to make a tougher and better looking
desk. He had shared some links of <a href="http://www.etsy.com/listing/105117201/modern-industrial-reclaimed-old-growth">tables</a> and <a href="http://www.the-brick-house.com/2009/09/shelving-unit/">bookcases</a> that people had
made using plumbing pipes, and reclaimed wood.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The Plan</h2>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/plans.jpg" title="The Plan" ></p>

<p>My plan was to to brace the legs near the bottom with an H-shape, and
connect the legs using T-joints, with end caps at the bottom, and
flanges at the top.</p>

<p>We wanted to use a solid wood table top, to make sure that it would be
very durable.</p>

<p>The total height would be 45 inches.</p>

<h2>Materials</h2>

<ul>
<li>IKEA NUMERAR Oak kitchen countertop ($129)</li>
<li>24 1-1/4" wood screws ($5)</li>
</ul>


<h3>Galvanized steel pipe, 1" thick</h3>

<ul>
<li>6 T-joints ($12 total)</li>
<li>4 flanges ($20 total)</li>
<li>4 end caps ($6 total)</li>
<li>4 1-inch extensions ($8 total)</li>
<li>4 couplings for the 1-inch extenssion ($7)</li>
<li>4 6-inch nipples ($16 total)</li>
<li>4 8-inch nipples ($20 total)</li>
<li>4 33-inch custom cut lengths ($40 total)</li>
<li>1 48-inch ($20)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Paint (for the pipes)</h2>

<ul>
<li>paint brush ($3)</li>
<li>latex gloves ($3)</li>
<li>white primer for galvanized steel or aluminum ($14)</li>
<li>matte black paint ($10)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Stain (for the desktop)</h2>

<ul>
<li>rags ($3)</li>
<li>paint brush ($3)</li>
<li>wood stain (Varathane in Early American) ($11)</li>
<li>polyurethane (satin finish)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Tools</h2>

<ul>
<li>Drill</li>
<li>Sandpaper, 180 and 220 grit ($5 total)</li>
<li>Sanding blocks ($7)</li>
<li>2 pairs of gloves ($3 each)</li>
<li>TSP substitute (for degreasing the pipes) ($7)</li>
<li>tarp to use as a drop cloth - 9 x 12' ($10)</li>
</ul>


<h1>Pipe shopping</h1>

<p>Plumbing supply stores and hardware stores have pre-cut lengths of pipe,
and the big ones like Lowe's and Home Depot will cut and thread specific lengths
for you for about $5 a cut.</p>

<p>I picked up my pipe at Lowe's where they cut my custom lengths right in
the aisle!</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/threading-machine.jpg" title="Steel cut and threading machine" ></p>

<p>To take them home in a Zipcar, we wrapped them in a plastic garbage bag,
so they wouldn't get greasy on the car (or on us!)</p>

<h2>Cleaning</h2>

<p>The first thing I did was wash them, using imitation TSP. It's a
solution that removes the grease, and leaves a slight tack on the steel
surface so that paint can stick to it.</p>

<h2>Assembly</h2>

<p>Then I screwed them together tightly, making sure that they were
the same height when attached.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/twisting.jpg" title="Twist together" ></p>

<p>I wore gloves because the threaded ends had some sharp bits.</p>

<h3>Durability testing</h3>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/moar-durability-testing.jpg" title="rugged" ></p>

<p>The frame was super strong!</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/tightrope.jpg" title="Tightrope" ></p>

<h2>White wash</h2>

<p>I primed the legs with the white paint, made specially for painting
galvanized steel.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/paint-white.jpg" title="White paint" ></p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/white-ta-da.jpg" title="drying" ></p>

<h2>Black out</h2>

<p>Next, I painted two coats of matte black.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/painted-black.jpg" title="Black paint" ></p>

<p>Now that the legs were done, I moved on to the desktop.</p>

<h1>The desktop</h1>

<p>To stick to a budget, we bought the <a href="http://www.ikea.com/us/en/catalog/products/40057396/">NUMERAR Countertop, oak, from
IKEA</a>.
It was $129, and super big. This isn't your typical IKEA furniture
quality, it is actually quite nice! My coworker (and victorian homeowner/restoration specialist) <a href="http://revictorian.com/">Val</a> tipped us off to it,
because she used it at home in her kitchen remodel.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/numerar-oak.jpg" title="Oak countertop" ></p>

<h2>Sanding</h2>

<p>I started by sanding it all over, first with 180 grit, and then with 220
grit.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/sanding-helper.jpg" title="Sanding helper" ></p>

<p>(I know that not all of us are fortunate enough to have a sanding helper,
but if you do, now is the time to utilize them!)</p>

<h2>Staining</h2>

<p>I tested out 4 different colors of stain by staining narrow strips on
the underside. I decided on "Early American" by Varathane. It wasn't
very far off from the natural color of the wood, it just added a slight
amount of richness.</p>

<p>I applied two coats to both sides and the edges of the table.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/stain-paint.jpg" title="Staining" ></p>

<h2>Sealing</h2>

<p>Next, I applied two coats of satin (the lowest gloss) polyurethane
sealant, so the wood would be protected from liquids and would be easier
to clean.</p>

<h1>Attaching top to bottom</h1>

<p>I put the table on the legs and verified that it was level.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/level.jpg" title="Level" ></p>

<p>I drilled guide holes before I screwed in each 1-1/4" wood screw.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/screws.jpg" title="Screws" ></p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/attach-screw.jpg" title="Attaching a screw" ></p>

<h1>Adding a monitor stand</h1>

<p>We wanted the monitor stand to be as rugged as the desk. I had two 8" blocks cut from a beam of 9"x4" pine.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/9by4.jpg" title="heavy lifting" ></p>

<p>It was only about $3 per cut, which seems like a deal given the amount
of work it was to carry this 20 foot beam to the cutting station!</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/monitor-stands.jpg" title="the blocks" ></p>

<p>I sanded and stained the blocks with leftover wood stain.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/monitor-stand-stain.jpg" title="sanded and stained" ></p>

<p>The final result was much better than a stack of textbooks!</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/monitor-stand.jpg" title="Stand plus duck" ></p>

<h1>Final result</h1>

<p>I was very happy with the final result! It is super sturdy, and has minimal wobble.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/from-above.jpg" title="From above" ></p>

<p>The desk is big enough to use as a pairing station, and looks good from
all sides.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/pipe-desk/pairs.jpg" title="Pairs" ></p>

<h3>Thanks!</h3>

<p>I couldn't have done it without help from my coworkers and friends!
Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/adelcambre">@adelcambre</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hone02">@hone02</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/ejgreenberg">@ejgreenberg</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/h">@h</a> (for modelling),
<a href="https://twitter.com/inrgbwetrust">@inrgbwetrust</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/mkb">@mkb</a>, and Lauren and Jean for helping me move things
around and supporting my nights painting upstairs at the office!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simple adjustable standing desk]]></title>
    <link href="http://spacekat.github.com/blog/2012/07/26/diy-standing-desk/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-26T20:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://spacekat.github.com/blog/2012/07/26/diy-standing-desk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The IKEA TV console hack</h2>

<p><img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/at-work.jpg" title="at work." ></p>

<p>For my first attempt and building a standing desk, I wanted to do something easy to to make, adjustable, and cheap.</p>

<h2>Materials</h2>

<ul>
<li>IKEA LACK TV unit. <em>($50)</em></li>
<li>IKEA GALANT adjustable A-frame desk legs <em>($15 each)</em> and base frame <em>($30)</em>.</li>
<li>6 bolts, 6 washers, and 6 nuts <em>(approx. $5)</em></li>
</ul>


<h2>Tools</h2>

<ul>
<li>Drill</li>
</ul>


<h3>Total Cost: $140</h3>

<!--more-->


<h3>Cubby inspiration</h3>

<p>One feature that I really wanted in a standing desk is some cubbie
space so that I could keep the desktop clear. The
<a href="https://www.buisjesenbeugels.nl/wonen/meubels/insekt-bureau-werk-geel-groen.html">INSEKT bureau +WORK</a> from Buisjes En Beugels in Rotterdam  is a gorgeous shape, and has tons of space inside the desktop.</p>

<h3>IKEA hunting</h3>

<p>I went to IKEA with a tape measure and started looking around at
furniture, keeping an open mind to what could be used as a desktop. A
lot of the TV consoles seemed like possible desktops, if they could have
very long legs underneath.</p>

<p>I chose a TV unit - the <a href="http://www.ikea.com/us/en/catalog/products/40105340/">LACK</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/lack-tv-unit.jpg" title="IKEA LACK tv unit" ></p>

<p>I measured my elbo height at 45". Without its legs, the LACK TV unit was 10" tall, leaving me with a difference of 35" to make up for in leg height.</p>

<p>In the desk and office furniture section, I found this adjustable A-Frame leg set, called <a href="http://www.ikea.com/us/en/catalog/products/S29806818/">GALANT</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.ikea.com/us/en/catalog/products/00105554/">GALANT A-leg</a> can reach a height of 35-5/8" when fully extended.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/galant-desk.jpg" title="GALANT desk" ></p>

<h2>IKEA funtimes</h2>

<p>I lugged the two items back to my office, to do some construction.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/haul.jpg" title="IKEA LACK and GALANT A-frame" ></p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/construction.jpg" title="Barefoot construction." >
<img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/construction-legs.jpg" title="A frame legs." ></p>

<h2>Attaching top to bottom</h2>

<p>The tricky bit was attaching the desktop to the leg frame!</p>

<p>Tricky, because if you've ever been poor, you know that IKEA wood is not
actually wood - inside the birch veneer is a cavity filled with with glue and
sawdust. It's not something that a wood screw could go into and stay
put.</p>

<p>So instead, I got six, 3" long, 1/4" bolts, to pierce from the toop surface all the
way through the holes in the frame.</p>

<h3>Prep</h3>

<p>I marked where to drill the holes for the bolts by flipping the frame
over.
<img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/upsidedown.jpg" title="Upside down." ></p>

<p>After centereing the frame, I marked the holes with a pen.
<img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/markinghole.jpg" title="Marking hole." ></p>

<h3>Black hole</h3>

<p>When it became time to drill, just how vacuous the surface the inside of
IKEA furniture is.
As soon as the bit breaks through the hard top veneer, it
goes into a land of mush. This mush clogged the drill bit quickly, so I
had to back out a few times for each hole.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/inside-ikea.jpg" title="drill jam." ></p>

<p>After the six holes were drilled, I set up the desk, lined it up with
the frame, and dropped in each of the bolts.
I put a fat washer on top of each bolt, since I wanted to make as much
contact with the surface (the hard part) as possible.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/bolts.jpg" title="big washer." ></p>

<p>Here's what the final setup looks like!</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/setup.jpg" title="setup." >
<img src="/images/blog/ikea-hax/at-work.jpg" title="at work." ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The (Almost) Freegan Standing Desk]]></title>
    <link href="http://spacekat.github.com/blog/2012/07/23/the-freegan-standing-desk/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-23T22:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://spacekat.github.com/blog/2012/07/23/the-freegan-standing-desk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Special challenge: Build a desk for under $30</h2>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-new-habitat.jpg" title="New Habitat" ></p>

<p>My friend <a href="http://ieatcupcakes.com/">Robin, the part-time cupcake chef,</a> and I are planning on going to Europe in a couple weeks. Needless to say, we want to save every bit of cash that we can for spending on important things like bicycle rentals in Berlin and flea markets in Paris.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>So for this desk, we wanted to see how little money we could spend. Robin
maintains that we could have done it for less than $5, if only we had an
additional week to forage for materials. She is probably right! But we didn't have time to do that much searching, and we still managed to construct a great desk for very little cost.</p>

<h2>Humble beginnings</h2>

<p>The basis of this desk was an abandoned table that <a href="https://twitter.com/calavera">David</a> spotted on the
sidewalk. The table was missing a leg, but the wooden table top was
usable, sturdy wood, it was just a bit dirty.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-free-desk.jpg" width="630" height="466" title="free desk" ></p>

<h2>Legs</h2>

<p>Next, we started to brainstorm what we could use for legs. Robin's desk needed to be a height of 43 inches. We thought about 2x4's, we thought about <a href="http://www.unistrut.us/index.php?WP=cat_detail&amp;S=S05&amp;P=P3000">UNISTRUT</a>, and we started looking through craigslist for tall table with legs we might be able to reappropriate. Then, Robin found a pair of narrow, short bookcases, by doing a keyword search for "42".</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-cl-headline.png" title="craigslist headline" ></p>

<p>The pair of bookcases, which once flanked a television, would be our
legs.
<img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-cl-bookcase.jpeg" title="Bookcases in their past life" ></p>

<p>The book shelfs would provide amble storage for the
books and supplies that inhabit Robin's current desk.</p>

<h2>Desktop</h2>

<p>I really liked the natural wood desktop, but Robin threatened to set it on fire - so to prevent any bouts of arson, we decided to paint it a poppy color of robin's egg blue.</p>

<div class="protip">
<p>
<em>Tip:</em> This paint was $3 at Kelly Moore, because it was in the "oopsies"
section.
</p>
</div>


<h3>Prep</h3>

<p>In preperation for paint, we did a little sanding.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-sanding.jpg" width="630" height="430" title="sanding the table top" ></p>

<div class="protip">
<p>
<em>Tip:</em> If you don't have a dropcloth or tarp, you can use an old shower
curtain.
</p>
</div>


<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-pre-paint.jpg" width="630" height="465" title="pre-paint" ></p>

<p>Next we propped it, and painted with a couple coats. We also painted the back of the bookcases (which were unsightly particle board before).</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/oopsie.jpg" title="oopsie" ></p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-painted-blue.jpg" width="630" height="465" title="painted blue" ></p>

<p>After finishing the desktop with aerosol spray top coat, we set it up in the driveway to check it out!</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-aerosol.jpg" title="spray coat" ></p>

<h2>Ta-daaaa</h2>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-setup.jpg" title="Check it out in the driveway" ></p>

<h2>Taking our desk to its new home</h2>

<p>Before screwing it together, we brought the desktop and legs to Robin's
office in the back of her super-Prius.</p>

<p>We dragged the old desk away, and setup the new desk in its place.</p>

<p>We secured the bookcases to the desktop with 1-3/4" wood screws from
inside the bookcase.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-drill.jpg" title="Drilling it together" ></p>

<h2>Desk Accessories</h2>

<p>On the desktop, Robin was concerned that her ever-growing collection of
beverages and snacks would cause a clutter, and could effect the surface
of the desk.</p>

<p>To get cheap organization accessories, we went to <a href="http://www.daiso-sangyo.co.jp/english/">DAISO</a>.</p>

<p>There, we procured this really cute polkadotted <em>Beverage tray</em> ($1.50).</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-tray.jpg" title="beverage tray" ></p>

<p>And this colorful <em>organizer tray</em> ($1.50).</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-organization.jpg" title="Organizer tray" ></p>

<h2>Gel mat for the floor</h2>

<p>Robin bought a gel pad for the floor at a restaurant supply store, where
she could buy it by the foot.
It was only $12.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/cash-and-carry-mat.jpg" title="gel mat" ></p>

<h2>Hooks</h2>

<p>The next day, Robin added hooks to hang her purse and jacket.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-hooks.jpg" title="Purse hooks" ></p>

<h2>Final Setup</h2>

<p>I had to run to take a bullet train back to SF, but here's how her desk
looked when I left.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/freegan-desk/freegan-new-habitat.jpg" title="New Habitat" ></p>

<p>The envy of all her office neighbors!</p>

<h2>Total Breakdown (The desk and all the accessories)</h2>

<ul>
<li>Paint ($3)</li>
<li>Desktop (Free)</li>
<li>Bookshelf legs ($25)</li>
<li>Drill, sandpaper, and hooks (Borrowed and donated)</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Desk Subtotal:</em> $28</p>

<ul>
<li>Desk accessories ($3)</li>
<li>Mat ($12)</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Grand Total:</em> $43</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
